Speaker: Judi Dench is one of a golden generation of British actors
who have had long and successful careers, including Maggie Smith, Vanessa Redgrave,
Ian McKellen, Michael Caine, and Anthony Hopkins.
She has acted in the theatre, on television, and in films in a career of nearly sixty years.
Judith Olivia Dench was born on the ninth of December
nineteen thirty-four in York in the north of England.
Dench’s father was a doctor, but she had connections from a very early age to the
Theatre Royal in York – her father was the theatre’s doctor
and her mother made costumes for the theatre.
As a teenager, Judi Dench acted in the York Mystery Plays.
These religious plays have been performed in York every four years since the fourteenth century.
In the late nineteen fifties and nineteen sixties, she acted with Britain’s most important theatre companies,
the Old Vic, the Royal Court, and the Royal Shakespeare Company.
In the nineteen seventies and nineteen eighties, Dench continued
to work in the theatre and on British television.
In nineteen seventy eight, she acted in Shakespeare’s Macbeth with the actor Ian McKellen,
both in the theatre and on film.
Many people think it was one of the best ever performances of the play.
She also appeared in British films like A Room with a View in nineteen eighty-five
And Henry V in nineteen eighty-nine.
In the nineteen nineties, her career changed with two films.
The first of these was the James Bond film, GoldenEye,
where Dench played Bond’s boss, M, normally a part for a man.
Dench was a great success in the part.
She was hard, and at the same time funny.
She played the part in eight films, with both Pierce Brosnan and Daniel Craig as James Bond.
The second film that changed her career was Mrs Brown in nineteen ninety-seven.
Dench played Queen Victoria.
This small, British film was a great success and she was nominated for an Oscar for Best Actress.
In nineteen ninety-eight, she played Queen Elizabeth the first in the comedy, Shakespeare in Love.
The film was another big hit.
It won the nineteen ninety-nine Oscar for Best Film,
and Judi Dench won the Oscar for Best Supporting Actress.
She’s only in the film for eight minutes, but, as ever, she’s absolutely brilliant.